# Miguel Xochicale

My research interests are in Real-time AI, Medical Imaging, MedTech and Biomechanics.

Research Engineer, advancing AI-based Surgical Navigation tools Advanced Research Computing Centre and WEISS University College London, UK

> ■ m.xochicale@ucl.ac.uk A http://mxochicale.github.io/ · In mxochicale

## **Education**

### Ph.D. in Computer Engineering at The University of Birmingham

Birmingham, UK

Thesis: Nonlinear Analysis to Quantify Movement Variability in Human-Humanoid Interaction.

Nov 2014 - Nov 2018

Supervisors: Professor Chris Baber and Professor Martin Russell

Awarded PhD degree: 12/07/2019. Thesis: 🚨 GitHub: 🖶 Website: 🗹

## M.Sc. in Signal Processing at Institute of Astrophysics, Optics and Electronics (INAOE)

Puebla, México

Thesis: Design of digital filters with fewer multipliers.

Supervisor: Dr. Gordana Jovanovic Dolecek

Awarded MSc degree: 01/11/2006. Thesis: 📙 GitHub: 🖶

Sep 2004 - Sep 2006

# Research Experience

#### Research Engineer at University College London, UK

Oct 2022 - Present

- Collaborators: Stephen Thompson, Dr Thomas Dowrick and Prof Matt Clarkson
- I am advacing AI-based Surgical Navigation tools with Python and CUDA programming languages via GitHub. See more at ( 🗹 ).

#### Research Associate in Real-time AI-based Ultrasound Imaging at King's College London, UKSep 2021 - Sep 2022

- · PIs: Dr Andrew King and Dr. Alberto Gomez
- I am scientifically contributing to automatic biometric recognition of Electrocardiography ultrasound data using real-time deep learning techniques and frameworks with Python, CUDA, C++ and Qt programming languages via GitHub. See more at ( 🗹 ).

#### Research Associate in Software and Hardware Engineering at King's College London, UK Apr 2019 – Aug 2021

- PIs: Prof. Tom Vercauteren and Dr. Wenfeng Xia
- · I pushed forward the state-of-the-art of Ultrasound-Guidance Interventions where was involved in the development of a needle tip tracking system, real-time ultrasound image processing, quality management system (QMS) for clinical translation of medical devices, and public engagement activities. See more at ( \(\mathbb{Z}\)).

# Supervision and Teaching Experience

King's College London	Jan 2020 – Present
• Supervision: Pablo Prieto Roca and Samuel Eyob. KURF projects on 3DGANs for fetal US imaging.	Jun 2022 – Aug 2022
• Supervision: Tsz Yan (Goosie) Leung, MSc in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Simple US guidance intervention	ı. Feb 2021 – Aug 2022
• Supervision: Thea Bautista, M. Eng. in Biomedical Engineering. Project: DCGANs for fetal US imaging.	Oct 2021 – May 2022
• Supervision: Guilherme Gomes de Figueiredo and Amal Hussein. KURF projects on DCGANs for US imaging.	Jun 2021 – Aug 2021
• Supervision: Alexander Mitton, M.Sc. in Medical Engineering and Physics. Project: Vibro-tactile stimulator for dystonia.	Jan 2020 – Sep 2020
Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Alejandro Granados	Jan 2022 – Apr 2022
Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Hongbin Liu	Jan 2021 – Apr 2021
Teaching Associate: Medical Robotics. Lecturer: Dr. Christos Bergeles	Jan 2020 – Apr 2020

### The University of Birmingham

Jun 2018 - Dec 2018

- · Supervision: Dinghuang Zhang, M.Sc. in Computer Engineering. Project: Tools for human-humanoid collaboration Aug 2018 - Dec 2018 Teaching associate: Engineering Maths 2. Lecturers: Prof. Martin Russell, Dr Carl Anthony Aug 2017 - Dec 2017; Jan 2018 - Apr2018
- Teaching Associate: Matlab Laboratories. Lecturer: Dr Edward Tarte Jan 2017 - Apr 2017
- Aug 2016 Dec 2016; Aug 2017 Dec 2017 Teaching Associate Computing for Engineering. Lecturer: Dr Sridhar Pammu
- Teaching Associate: Small Embedded Systems. Lecturer: Prof. Chris Baber

#### Aug 2016 - Dec 2016

#### **Teaching Associate at Mexican Institutions**

Aug 2006 – Dec 2013 Teaching Associate at Bilingual Hight School TECMilenio University, Puebla, México. Aug 2013 - Dec 2013 Jan 2012 - Dec 2012 Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng at Universidad Madero, Puebla, México. Teaching Associate in Electronic Eng. at Universidad Iberoamericana Puebla, Puebla, México. Jan 2007 - Dec 2011 Teaching Associate in Mechatronic Eng. at Instituto Tecnológico Superior de Atlixco, Puebla, México. Aug 2006 - Jun 2007

# **Publications**

- 1. T. Bautista, J. Matthew, H. Kerdegari, L. Peralta, and M. Xochicale, "Empirical study of quality image assessment for synthesis of fetal head ultrasound imaging with dcgans," in 26th UK Conference on Medical Image Understanding and Analysis (MIUA '22), arXiv, Jun. 2022, 3-page abstract, code and data.
- 2. E. Puyol-Antón, B. Ruijsink, B. S. Sidhu, et al., Ai-enabled assessment of cardiac systolic and diastolic function from echocardiography, Mar. 2022. arXiv: 2203.11726 [physics.med-ph; cs.CV; eess.IV], Full Manuscript.
- 3. A. Badillo-Perez, D. Badillo-Perez, D. Coyotzi-Molina, D. Cruz, R. Montenegro, L. Vazquez, and M. Xochicale, "Piloting diversity and inclusion workshops in artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 17th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '22), Mar. 2022.
- 4. R. Beale, J. B. Rosendo, C. Bergeles, et al., "Oxvent: Design and evaluation of a rapidly-manufactured covid-19 ventilator," eBioMedicine, vol. 76, p. 103 868, 2022.
- 5. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear methods to quantify movement variability in human-humanoid interaction activities," Mar. 2021. arXiv: 1810.09249 [eess.SP], Full Manuscript.

- 6. R. Montenegro, E. Corona, D. Badillo-Perez, A. Mandujano, L. Vazquez, D. Cruz, and M. Xochicale, "Air4children: Artificial intelligence and robotics for children," in 16th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '21), Feb. 2021. arXiv: 2103.07637 [cs.R0].
- 7. C. Baker, M. Xochicale, F. Joubert, et al., "Real-time ultrasonic tracking of an intraoperative needle tip with integrated fibre-optic hydrophone," in 2021 IEEE International Ultrasonics Symposium (IUS), 2021, pp. 1-4.
- 8. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability in human-humanoid imitation activities," in 5th International Conference on Human Agent Interaction (HAI '17), Bielefeld, Germany, Oct. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 9. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Towards the quantification of human-robot imitation using wearable inertial sensors," in 12th Annual Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI '17), Vienna, Austria, Mar. 2017, Poster Paper.
- 10. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Analysis of the movement variability in dance activities using wearable sensors," in 2nd International Symposium on Wearable Robotics (WeRob '16), Segovia, Spain, Oct. 2016, Poster Paper.
- 11. M. Xochicale, C. Baber, and O. Mourad, "Understanding movement variability of simplistic gestures using an inertial sensor," in 5th ACM International Symposium on Pervasive Displays (PerDis '16), Oulu, Finland, Jun. 2016, Poster Paper.

## Talks and Posters

- 1. M. Xochicale, "Fetal ultrasound imaging synthesis," Data Learning Seminar at Imperial College London, Sep. 2022, Presentation Abstract.
- 2. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Nonlinear analysis to quantify human movement variability from time-series data," in neuromatch 3.0 (NMC3 '20), Virtual Conference, Oct. 2020, Presentation Abstract.
- M. Xochicale, "Open-cortex: A continuous integration framework for open scientific communication," in 1st Conference on Reproducibility, Replicability and Trust in Science (RRTS '20), Cambridge, England (Virtual Conference), Sep. 2020, Poster Abstract.
- 4. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying movement variability with nonlinear dynamics for human-humanoid interaction," in 25th International Conference on Difference Equations and Applications (ICDEA '19), London, UK, Jun. 2019, Slices abstract.
- 5. M. Xochicale, "Quantification of dynamic facial expressions with shannon entropy in human-humanoid interaction," in 1st Symposium on Machine Learning and Dynamical Systems (MLDS '19), London, UK, Feb. 2019, Poster Abstract.
- 6. M. Xochicale, "Quantifying the inherent chaos of human movement variability," in 15th Experimental Chaos and Complexity Conference (ECCC '18), Madrid, Spain, Jun. 2018, Presentation Abstract.
- 7. M. Xochicale and C. Baber, "Towards the analysis of movement variability for facial expressions with nonlinear dynamics," in 7th Consortium of European Research on Emotion Conference (CERE '18), Glasgow, Scotland, UK, Apr. 2018, Presentation abstract.

## Grants, Awards and Honours

- King's Public Engagement grant for the project "FETUS: Finding a fETus with an Ultrasound Simulator" led by myself and in collaboration with Fang-Yu Lin and Shu Wang 🗹
- My M.Sc. student, Alexander Mitton, won the Outstanding Individual Project award 🗹 (15/10/2020)
- King's Health Partners grant for the project "Sensory system abnormalities in childhood dystonia" lead by Verity McClelland and in collaboration with Carlos Seneci 🗹 (14/04/2020 - 9/06/2020)
- My work "Towards Healthy Ageing with Humanoid Robots" was selected for a talk at the second forum of Mexican Talent, Innovation Match MX 2017, 🗹 🚨 🖸
- I won the best poster award at the XIV Symposium of Mexican Students in the UK at University of Edinburgh 🗹 16-18/06/2016 My project of a low-cost robot was selected among 125 applications received from 35 countries and presented at the first international public 20-24/07/2015
- entrepreneurship program in Mexico (MECATE 2015). 🗹 🖸 I won a Ph.D. scholarship by the Mexican National Council on Science and Technology. 11/2014-11/2018
- Markovito's team won the first place at the Mexican Tournament of Robotics 2013 in the category at HOME where I presented a Human-Robot Interaction Dance Demo.

## Skills

Programming Python[2014-present], R[2013-present], Robot Operating System (ROS)[2016-present], GNU-Octave (or MatLab)[2009-present], LATEX[2006-present], C and C++[2015-present], Processing[2012-present], the shell[2010-present], GNU-emacs[2010-present], vim[2016-present] present], pandoc[2017-present], open-source enthusiast at GitHub (@mxochicale)[2015-present], continuous integration and continuous delivery [2019-present], and CUDA Programming [2021-present].

Tools GNU/Linux Operating System user (e.g. OpenSuse, Debian and Ubuntu)[2005-present] Single-board computers and microcontrollers (e.g. NVIDIA Jetson Nano, RaspberryPi, BeagleBone, Arduino and PIC)[2010-present], Inertial Measurement Units (e.g. calibration, collection and data analysis)[2013-present], Web design (e.g. Github pages, Jekyll)[2015-present], and Graphic design (e.g. Inkscape, GIMP)[2014-present], CAD design (e.g. Autodesk invetor, blender, FreeCAD)[2015-present], Artificial Neural Networks (e.g. PyTorch, and TensorFlow)[2017-present], 3D printing (e.g., flsun, cura) [2019-present], Video framegrabbers (e.g. PCI and usb from ephipan), and Medical imaging (e.g. 3D slicer, ITK-SNAP).

QMS Control documents with standard complience for Good Machine Learning Practice by FDA, Health Canada, and MHRA; IEC 62304 Medical Device Software Standard; BS EN 82304-1:2017 Health Software; IEC 60601-1 Medical electrical equipment; BS EN 61391-2:2010 Ultrasonics;, and BSI 60825-14 Safety of laser products.

Languages Spanish[Native], English[Fluent] and interested in learning Chinese.

# Outreach activities and scientific engagement

- - Organised events on behalf of the Early Career Researcher Network at the BMEIS 01-01-2021 - 01-09-2022.
- Participation in the Westminster Enterprise Week to engage students aged 14-18 to Biomedical Engineering. 10-11-2021 Participant in the STEAM WEEK organised by the City Westminster Council to engage students aged 14-18 to STEAM 🔰 23-03-2021
- Alexandra Lautarescu and I organised the Reproducible, Interpretable, Open, & Transparent Science Club at BMEIS 02-2020 - 06-2020
- For the event In2ScienceUK, I shared my scientific journey to young scientist on how they can become better scientist. 20-08-2019
- For the New Scientist Live, I showcased software that helps doctors to create 3D models of brain tumors using AI. 09-2019
- 05-2018
- Finalist at the Three Minute Thesis Competition 2018. Video: 🖸 and GitHub: 👼
- Research Poster Conference for (2015) 🔼, (2016) 🚨, and (2018) 🔼. GitHub: 👼. 2016 to 2018
- 2014-2018 Demoing Human-Robot Activities at the Undergraduate Open Days. GitHub: .
- Coordinator of the Science Seminars for the Mexican Society. GitHub: 👼 , Website: 🗹 2017-2018
- Building Artificial Intelligence and Robotics for Children. Twitter: 💆 @air4children GitHub: 🖶 @air4children 2019-Present

10/11-11-2022.